<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- lifted from troff+man by doclifter -->
<refentry>
<refentryinfo>
  <author><firstname>Paul</firstname><surname>Wouters</surname><authorblurb><para>placeholder to suppress warning</para> </authorblurb></author>
</refentryinfo>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>IPSEC.SECRETS</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>17 April 2014</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="source">libreswan</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">Executable programs</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>ipsec.secrets</refname>
<refpurpose>secrets for IKE/IPsec authentication</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para>The file <filename>ipsec.secrets</filename> contains
a list of secrets. Currently supported secrets are preshared
secrets (PSKs), RSA keys and XAUTH passwords. These secrets are used by
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>pluto</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
, the Libreswan Internet Key Exchange daemon, to authenticate other hosts.
</para>

<para>RSA private keys are stored in the NSS database. The secrets file only contains a reference to these private RSA keys. For RSA
keys belonging to imported X.509 certificates, the certificate "friendly name" is used. For raw RSA keys, the CKAID is used.</para>

<para>XAUTH passwords are stored in plaintext in this file. The secrets file should be owned
by root, and permissions should be set to block all access by others. (eg: chmod 600)</para>

<para>The file is a sequence of entries and include directives.
Here is an example - each entry or directive must start at the
left margin, but if it continues beyond a single line, each continuation
line must be indented.
<literallayout remap='.nf'>
# sample @IPSEC_SECRETS_FILE@ file for 10.1.0.1
10.1.0.1 10.2.0.1 : PSK "secret shared by two hosts"
# sample roadwarrior
%any gateway.corp.com : PSK "shared secret with many roadwarriors"
# sample server for roadwarriors
myip %any : PSK "shared secret with many roadwarriors"

# an entry may be split across lines,
# but indentation matters
www.xs4all.nl @www.kremvax.ru
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;10.6.0.1 10.7.0.1 1.8.0.1 : PSK "secret shared by 5 systems"

# a raw RSA private key in NSS. All but the public exponent now point
# to the NSS CKAIDNSS
# note that the lines are too wide for a
# man page, so ... has been substituted for
# the truncated part
@my.com : RSA {
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;#pubkey=0sAQPaGwWbUSK...
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;PublicExponent:&nbsp;0x03
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;PrivateExponent:&nbsp;0x316e6593...
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Prime1:&nbsp;0x316e6593...
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Prime2:&nbsp;0x316e6593...
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Exponent1:&nbsp;0x316e6593...
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Exponent2:&nbsp;0x316e6593...
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Coefficient:&nbsp;0x316e6593...
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;CKAIDNSS:&nbsp;0x316e6593...
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;}

# an imported X.509 certificate in NSS
: RSA "&lt;friendly name&gt;"

# XAUTH password, used with leftxauthusername=username
@username : XAUTH "password"

include ipsec.*.secrets	# get secrets from other files
</literallayout> <!-- .fi -->

Each entry in the file is a list of indices, followed by a secret.
The two parts are separated by a colon (<emphasis remap='B'>:</emphasis>) that is
followed by whitespace or a newline. </para>

<para>An index is an IP address, or a Fully Qualified
Domain Name, user@FQDN, <emphasis remap='B'>%any</emphasis>
or <emphasis remap='B'>%any6</emphasis> (other kinds
may come).  An IP address may be written in the familiar
dotted quad form or as a domain name to be looked up when the
file is loaded (or in any of the forms supported by the Libreswan
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_ttoaddr</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry>
routine).  Be aware that using domain names requires DNS to be functional
before the IPsec tunnel comes up.  To denote a Fully Qualified Domain
Name (as opposed to an IP address denoted by its domain name), precede
the name with an at sign (<emphasis remap='B'>@</emphasis>).</para>

<para>Matching IDs with indices is fairly straightforward: they have to be
equal.  In the case of a &ldquo;Road Warrior&rdquo; connection, if an equal
match is not found for the Peer's ID, and it is in the form of an IP
address, an index of <emphasis remap='B'>%any</emphasis> will match the peer's IP address if IPV4
and <emphasis remap='B'>%any6</emphasis> will match a the peer's IP address if IPV6.
</para>

<para>This file is only read at startup time. If any changes are made to this file,
the pluto daemon should be told to re-read this file using the command
<emphasis remap='B'>ipsec secrets</emphasis> or <emphasis remap='B'>ipsec auto --rereadsecrets</emphasis>.
Note that currently there is no way to add a specific new entry - it's
all or nothing.</para>

<para>Smartcard support has been moved from Libreswan to NSS. Please see the NSS
documentation on how to configure smartcards.</para>

<para>An additional complexity arises in the case of authentication by preshared
secret: the responder will need to look up the secret before the Peer's ID payload has
been decoded, so the ID used will be the IP address.</para>

<para>To authenticate a connection between two hosts, the entry that most
specifically matches the host and peer IDs is used.  An entry with no
index will match any host and peer.  More specifically, an entry with one index will
match a host and peer if the index matches the host's ID (the peer isn't
considered).  Still more specifically, an entry with multiple indices will match a host and
peer if the host ID and peer ID each match one of the indices.  If the key
is for an asymmetric authentication technique (i.e. a public key
system such as RSA), an entry with multiple indices will match a host
and peer even if only the host ID matches an index (it is presumed that the
multiple indices are all identities of the host).
It is acceptable for two entries to be the best match as
long as they agree about the secret or private key.</para>

<para>Authentication by preshared secret requires that both systems find the
identical secret (the secret is not actually transmitted by the IKE
protocol).  If both the host and peer appear in the index list, the
same entry will be suitable for both systems so verbatim copying
between systems can be used.  This naturally extends to larger groups
sharing the same secret.  Thus multiple-index entries are best for PSK
authentication.</para>

<para>Authentication by raw RSA Signatures requires that each host have its own private
key.  A host could reasonably use a different private keys
for different interfaces and for different peers.  But it would not
be normal to share entries between systems.  Thus no-index and
one-index forms of entry often make sense for RSA Signature authentication.</para>

<para>The key part of an entry may start with a token indicating the kind of
key.  &ldquo;RSA&rdquo; signifies RSA private key and &ldquo;PSK&rdquo; signifies
PreShared Key (case is ignored). </para>

<para>The token &ldquo;XAUTH&rdquo; indicates
a eXtended Authentication password. There should be one indice, and it
should be in the @FQDN format. The file will be searched with the XAUTH
username, which is usually provided in the configuration file.
XAUTH is otherwise identical to PSK in syntax.
</para>

<para>A preshared secret is most conveniently represented as a sequence of
characters, delimited by the double-quote
character (<emphasis remap='B'>"</emphasis>).  The sequence cannot contain a newline or
double-quote.  Strictly speaking, the secret is actually the sequence
of bytes that is used in the file to represent the sequence of
characters (excluding the delimiters).
A preshared secret may also be represented, without quotes, in any form supported by
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_ttodata</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry>.</para>

<para>A raw RSA private key is a composite of eight generally large numbers.  The notation
used is a brace-enclosed list of field name and value pairs (see the example above).
A suitable key, in a suitable format, may be generated by <citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_rsasigkey</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
The structure is very similar to that used by BIND 8.2.2 or later, but note that
the numbers must have a &ldquo;0s&rdquo; prefix if they are in base 64.  The order of
the fields is fixed. Note that most fields are now unused and filled in with the CKAID, which is a reference
to the location within the NSS database.</para>

<para>The first token of an entry must start in the first column of its line.  Subsequent tokens must be
separated by whitespace, except for a colon token, which only needs to be followed by whitespace.
A newline is taken as whitespace, but every line of an entry after the first must be indented.</para>

<para>Whitespace at the end of a line is ignored (except in the 0t
notation for a key).  At the start of line or
after whitespace, <emphasis remap='B'>#</emphasis> and the following text up to the end of the
line is treated as a comment.  Within entries, all lines must be
indented (except for lines with no tokens).
Outside entries, no line may be indented (this is to make sure that
the file layout reflects its structure).</para>

<para>An include directive causes the contents of the named file to be processed
before continuing with the current file.  The filename is subject to
&ldquo;globbing&rdquo; as in <citerefentry><refentrytitle>sh</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, so every file with a matching name is processed.  Includes may be nested to a modest
depth (10, currently).  If the filename doesn't start with a <emphasis remap='B'>/</emphasis>, the
directory containing the current file is prepended to the name.  The
include directive is a line that starts with the word <emphasis remap='B'>include</emphasis>,
followed by whitespace, followed by the filename (which must not contain
whitespace).</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='files'><title>FILES</title>
<para>@IPSEC_SECRETS_FILE@</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para>The rest of the Libreswan distribution, in particular
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec.conf</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_newhostkey</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_rsasigkey</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_showhostkey</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_auto</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> <option>--rereadsecrets</option>,
and <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pluto</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry> <option>--listen</option>.
</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='history'><title>HISTORY</title>
<para>Originally designed for the FreeS/WAN project
&lt;<ulink url='http://www.freeswan.org'>http://www.freeswan.org</ulink>&gt; by
D. Hugh Redelmeier.  Updated for Openswan by Ken Bantoft. Updated for
Libreswan by Paul Wouters</para> <para>This file originally stored the
private part of RSA keys. All private key material is now stored in
the NSS database. The fields of the raw RSA key currently filled with
the CKAID might be ignored and removed in future versions.  </para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='bugs'><title>BUGS</title>
<para>If an ID is <literal>0.0.0.0</literal>, it will match <emphasis remap='B'>%any</emphasis>;
if it is <emphasis remap='B'>0::0</emphasis>, it will match <emphasis remap='B'>%any6</emphasis>.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

