<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- lifted from troff+man by doclifter -->
<refentry>
<refentryinfo>
  <author><firstname>Paul</firstname><surname>Wouters</surname><authorblurb><para>placeholder to suppress warning</para> </authorblurb></author>
</refentryinfo>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>IPSEC_RSASIGKEY</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>6 Sep 2013</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="source">libreswan</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">Executable programs</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>ipsec rsasigkey</refname>
<refpurpose>generate RSA signature key</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>
<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>ipsec</command>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>rsasigkey</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>--verbose </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>--seeddev <replaceable>device</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>--seed <replaceable>numbits</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>--configdir <replaceable>nssdbdir</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>--password <replaceable>nsspassword</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>--hostname <replaceable>hostname</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>nbits </arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>


<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para><emphasis remap='I'>Rsasigkey</emphasis>
generates an RSA public/private key pair, suitable for digital signatures, of (exactly)
<emphasis remap='I'>nbits</emphasis> bits (that is, two primes each of exactly
<emphasis remap='I'>nbits</emphasis>/2 bits, and related numbers) and emits it on standard
 output as ASCII (mostly hex) data. <emphasis remap='I'>nbits</emphasis> must be a multiple of 16.
</para>

<para>The public exponent is forced to the value <emphasis remap='B'>3</emphasis>, which has important
speed advantages for signature checking. Beware that the resulting keys have known weaknesses as encryption keys
<emphasis remap='B'>and should not be used for that purpose</emphasis>.</para>

<para>The <option>--verbose</option> option makes <emphasis
remap='I'>rsasigkey</emphasis> give a running commentary on standard
error. By default, it works in silence until it is ready to generate
output.</para>

<para>The <option>--seeddev</option> option specifies a
source for random bits used to seed the crypto library's
RNG. The default is <filename>/dev/random</filename> (see
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>random</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry>).
FreeS/WAN and Openswan without NSS support used this option to specify
the random source used to directly create keys. Libreswan only uses
it to seed the NSS crypto libraries RNG. Under Linux with hardware random
support, special devices might show up as <filename>/dev/*rng*</filename>
devices. However, these should never be accessed directly using this option,
as hardware failures could lead to extremely non-random values (streams
of zeroes have been observed in the wild) </para>

<para>The <option>--seedbits</option> option specifies how many seed bits are pulled from
the random device to seed the NSS PRNG. The default of 480bit comes from FIPS requirements.
Seed bits are rounded up to a multiple of 8.
</para>

<para>The use of a different random device or a reduction of seedbits from the default value is
prevented when the system is running in FIPS mode.</para>

<para>The <option>--configdir</option> option specifies the nss configuration directory to use.
This is the directory where the NSS certificate, key and security modules databases reside. The
default value is <filename>/etc/ipsec.d</filename>.</para>

<para>The <option>--password</option> option specifies the nss cryptographic module authentication
password if the NSS module has been configured to require it.  A password is required by hardware
tokens and also by the internal software token module when configured to run in FIPS mode.
If the argument is <emphasis remap='I'>configdir</emphasis><filename>/nsspassword</filename>, the password comes from that file;
otherwise argument is the password.
</para>

<para>The <option>--hostname</option> option specifies what host name to use in the first line
of the output (see below); the default is what
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gethostname</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum></citerefentry>
returns.</para>

<para> The output format looks like this (with long numbers trimmed down for clarity):
<literallayout remap='.nf'>

	# RSA 2048 bits   xy.example.com   Sat Apr 15 13:53:22 2000
	# for signatures only, UNSAFE FOR ENCRYPTION
	#pubkey=0sAQOF8tZ2NZt...Y1P+buFuFn/
	#ckaid=7ddad7f1d5842e...043c499babf0a
	Modulus: 0xcc2a86fcf440...cf1011abb82d1
	PublicExponent: 0x03

</literallayout> <!-- .fi -->
The first (comment) line, indicating the nature and date of the key, and
giving a host name, is used by
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_showhostkey</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
when generating some forms of key output.</para>

<para>The commented-out <option>pubkey=</option> line contains the public key,
the public exponent and the modulus combined in approximately RFC 2537 format
(the one deviation is that the combined value is given with a
<emphasis remap='I'>0s</emphasis> prefix, rather than in unadorned base-64),
suitable for use in the <filename>ipsec.conf</filename> file.</para>

<para>The <option>Modulus</option>, <option>PublicExponent</option> and <option>PrivateExponent</option>
lines give the basic signing and verification data.</para>

<para>The <option>Prime1</option> and <option>Prime2</option> lines give the
primes themselves (aka <emphasis remap='I'>p</emphasis> and <emphasis remap='I'>q</emphasis>),
largest first. The <option>Exponent1</option> and <option>Exponent2</option>
lines give the private exponent mod <emphasis remap='I'>p-1</emphasis> and
<emphasis remap='I'>q-1</emphasis> respectively. The <option>Coefficient</option>
line gives the Chinese Remainder Theorem coefficient, which is the inverse of
<emphasis remap='I'>q</emphasis>, mod <emphasis remap='I'>p</emphasis>. These
additional numbers (which must all be kept as secret as the private
exponent) are precomputed aids to rapid signature generation.  When NSS
is used, these values are not available outside the NSS security database
(software token or hardware token) and are instead filled in with the CKA_ID.
</para>
<para>No attempt is made to break long lines.</para>

<para> The US patent on the RSA algorithm expired 20 Sept 2000.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='examples'><title>EXAMPLES</title>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
 <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>ipsec rsasigkey --verbose 4096 >mykey.txt</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
   <para>generates a 4096-bit signature key  and  puts  it  in  the  file <filename>mykey.txt</filename>,
    with running commentary on standard error.  The file contents can be inserted verbatim into  a  suitable  entry  in  the
    <filename>ipsec.secrets</filename> file (see
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_secrets</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>),
    and the public key can then be extracted and edited into the <filename>ipsec.conf</filename> (see
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_showhostkey</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>).
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='files'><title>FILES</title>
<para>/dev/random, /dev/urandom</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para>
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>random</refentrytitle><manvolnum>4</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>rngd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_showhostkey</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<emphasis remap='I'>Applied Cryptography, 2nd. ed., by Bruce Schneier, Wiley 1996</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>RFCs 2537, 2313</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='I'>GNU  MP, the GNU multiple precision arithmetic library, edition 2.0.2, by Torbj Granlund</emphasis>
</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='history'><title>HISTORY</title>
<para>Originally written for the Linux FreeS/WAN project
&lt;<ulink url='http://www.freeswan.org'>http://www.freeswan.org</ulink>&gt;
by Henry Spencer. Updated for the Libreswan Project by Paul Wouters.</para>
<para>The <emphasis remap='I'>--round</emphasis> and <emphasis remap='I'>--noopt</emphasis>
options were obsoleted as these were only used with the old non-library crypto code</para>
<para>The <emphasis remap='I'>--random</emphasis> device is only used for seeding the crypto library,
not for direct random to generate keys</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='bugs'><title>BUGS</title>
<para>There is an internal limit on
<emphasis remap='I'>nbits</emphasis>,
currently 20000.</para>
<para><emphasis remap='I'>rsasigkey</emphasis>'s run time is difficult
to predict, since <filename>/dev/random</filename> output can
be arbitrarily delayed if the system's entropy pool is low on
randomness, and  the time taken by the search for primes is also somewhat
unpredictable. Specifically, embedded systems and most virtual machines are low on
entropy. In such a situation, consider generating the RSA key on another machine,
and copying <filename>ipsec.secrets</filename> and the <filename>ipsec.d/*db</filename>
files to the embedded platform. Note that NSS embeds the full path in the DB files, so
the path on proxy machine must be identical to the path on the destination machine.
</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

