  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>authby</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>how the two security gateways should authenticate each other;
the default value is <emphasis remap='B'>rsasig,ecdsa</emphasis> which allows
ECDSA with SHA-2 and RSA with SHA-1 or SHA2. To limit this further, there are
the options of
<emphasis remap='B'>ecdsa</emphasis> for ECDSA digital signatures using SHA-2,
<emphasis remap='B'>rsa-sha2</emphasis> for RSASSA-PSS digital signatures based
authentication with SHA2-256,
<emphasis remap='B'>rsa-sha2_384</emphasis> for RSASSA-PSS digital signatures based
authentication with SHA2-384,
<emphasis remap='B'>rsa-sha2_512</emphasis> for RSASSA-PSS digital signatures based
authentication with SHA2-512,
<emphasis remap='B'>rsa-sha1</emphasis> for RSA-PKCSv1.5 digital signatures based
authentication with SHA1,
<emphasis remap='B'>secret</emphasis> for shared secrets (PSK) authentication,
<emphasis remap='B'>secret|rsasig</emphasis> for either,
<emphasis remap='B'>never</emphasis> if negotiation is never to be attempted
or accepted (useful for shunt-only conns), and
<emphasis remap='B'>null</emphasis> for null-authentication.
</para>
<para>
If asymmetric authentication is requested, IKEv2 must be enabled, and the
options <emphasis remap='B'>leftauth=</emphasis> and <emphasis remap='B'>rightauth=</emphasis>
should be used instead of authby.
</para>
<para>
For IKEv1, SHA2 based signatures are not defined and ECDSA is not implemented, so the
default authby= value is rsa-sha1. Using authby=rsasig results in only rsa-sha1 as well.
For IKEv2, using authby=rsasig means using rsa-sha2, rsa-sha2_384,rsa-sha2_512, rsa-sha1,
where rsa-sha1 will used only if RFC 7427 is not supported by the peer.
</para>
<para>
As per RFC 8221, authby=rsa-sha1 is only supported in the old style, meaning RSA-PKCSv1.5.
The SHA2 variants are only supported for the new style of RFC 7427, so authby=rsa-sha2 will
use the new style. The default authby= will remove rsa-sha1 in the near future. It is strongly
recommended that if certificates are used, the certificates and the authby= signature methods
used are the same, as it increases interoperability and keeps the authentication of everything
within one digital signature system.
</para>
<para>
Digital signatures are superior in every way to shared secrets. Especially
IKEv1 in Aggressive Mode is vulnerable to offline dictionary attacks and
is performed routinely by at least the NSA on monitored internet traffic
globally. The never option is only used for connections that do not actually
start an IKE negotiation, such as type=passthrough connections. The auth
method null is used for "anonymous opportunistic IPsec" and should not be
used for regular pre-configured IPsec VPNs.
 </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
