<refsect1 id='description'>
  <title>
    DESCRIPTION
  </title>
  <para>
    The <emphasis>ipsec.conf</emphasis> file specifies most
    configuration and control information for the Libreswan IPsec
    subsystem.  (The major exception is secrets for authentication;
    see
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec.secrets</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>.)
    Its contents are not security-sensitive. Configurations can be
    added using this configuration file or by using ipsec whack
    directly. This means that technically, the ipsec.conf file is
    optional, but a few warnings might show up when this file is
    missing.
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis>ipsec.conf</emphasis> is a text file,
    consisting of one or more <emphasis>sections</emphasis>.
    White space followed by <emphasis>#</emphasis> followed
    by anything to the end of the line is a comment and is ignored, as
    are empty lines that are not within a section.
  </para>

  <para>
    A line that contains <emphasis>include</emphasis> and a
    file name, separated by white space, is replaced by the contents
    of that file, preceded and followed by empty lines.  If the file
    name is not a full pathname, it is considered to be relative to
    the directory that contains the including file.  Such inclusions
    can be nested.  Only a single filename may be supplied, and it may
    not contain white space, but it may include shell wildcards (see
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>sh</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>);
    for example:
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis>include </emphasis> <emphasis>/etc/ipsec.d/*.conf</emphasis>
  </para>

  <para>
    The intention of the include facility is mostly to permit keeping
    information on connections, or sets of connections, separate from
    the main configuration file.  This permits such connection
    descriptions to be changed, copied to the other security gateways
    involved, etc., without having to constantly extract them from the
    configuration file and then insert them back into it.  Note also
    the <emphasis>also</emphasis>
    parameters (described below) which permit splitting a single
    logical section (e.g. a connection description) into several
    distinct sections.
  </para>

  <para>
    The first significant line of the file may specify a version of
    this specification for backwards compatibility with freeswan and
    openswan. It is ignored and unused. For compatibility with
    openswan, specify:
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis>version 2</emphasis>
  </para>

  <para>
    A section begins with a line of the form:
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis>type</emphasis> <emphasis>name</emphasis>
  </para>

  <para>
    where <emphasis>type</emphasis> indicates what type of
    section follows, and <emphasis>name</emphasis> is an
    arbitrary name that distinguishes the section from others of the
    same type.  (Names must start with a letter and may contain only
    letters, digits, periods, underscores, and hyphens.)  All
    subsequent non-empty lines that begin with white space are part of
    the section; comments within a section must begin with white space
    too.  There may be only one section of a given type with a given
    name.
  </para>

  <para>
    Lines within the section are generally of the form
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis>parameter</emphasis><emphasis>=</emphasis><emphasis>value</emphasis>
  </para>

  <para>
    (note the mandatory preceding white space).  There can be white
    space on either side of the <emphasis>=</emphasis>.
    Parameter names follow the same syntax as section names, and are
    specific to a section type.  Unless otherwise explicitly
    specified, no parameter name may appear more than once in a
    section.
  </para>

  <para>
    An empty <emphasis>value</emphasis> stands for the
    system default value (if any) of the parameter, i.e. it is roughly
    equivalent to omitting the parameter line entirely.
    A <emphasis>value</emphasis> may contain white space only if the
    entire <emphasis>value</emphasis> is enclosed in double
    quotes (<emphasis>"</emphasis>); a <emphasis>value</emphasis>
    cannot itself contain a double quote, nor may it be continued
    across more than one line.
  </para>

  <para>
    Numeric values are specified to be either an &ldquo;integer&rdquo;
    (a sequence of digits) or a &ldquo;decimal number&rdquo; (sequence
    of digits optionally followed by `.' and another sequence of
    digits).
  </para>

  <para>
    There is currently one parameter that is available in any type of
    section:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>also</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The value is a section name.  The parameters of that section
	  are inserted, in place, into this section (i.e., as if they
	  had been written as part of and at that point in the
	  section's definition).  The specified section must exist,
	  and must have the same section type.  Multiple and nested
	  <emphasis>also</emphasis> are permitted (duplicate
	  insertions of the same section are ignored).  This allows,
	  for example, keeping the encryption keys for a connection in
	  a separate file from the rest of the description, by using
	  both an <emphasis>also</emphasis> parameter and an
	  <emphasis>include</emphasis> line.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
    Parameter names beginning with <emphasis>x-</emphasis>
    (or <emphasis>X-</emphasis>, or <emphasis>x_</emphasis>,
    or <emphasis>X_</emphasis>) are reserved for user extensions
    and will never be assigned meanings by IPsec.
    Parameters with such names must still observe the syntax rules
    (limits on characters used in the name; no white space in
    a non-quoted value; no newlines or double quotes within the value).
    All other as-yet-unused parameter names are reserved for future IPsec
    improvements.
  </para>

  <para>
    A section with name <emphasis>%default</emphasis>
    specifies defaults for sections of the same type.  For each
    parameter in it, any section of that type that does not have a
    parameter of the same name gets a copy of the one from the
    <emphasis>%default</emphasis> section.  There may be
    multiple <emphasis>%default</emphasis> sections of a
    given type, but only one default may be supplied for any specific
    parameter name.  <emphasis>%default</emphasis> sections
    may not contain any <emphasis>also</emphasis> parameters.
  </para>

  <para>
    Currently there are two types of section: a <emphasis>config</emphasis>
    section specifies general configuration information for IPsec,
    while a <emphasis>conn</emphasis> section specifies an IPsec connection.
  </para>
</refsect1>

