<refsect1 id='description'>

  <title>
    DESCRIPTION
  </title>

  <para>
    The <filename>ipsec.conf</filename> file specifies most configuration and
    control information for the <application>Libreswan</application>
    IPsec subsystem  (the major
    exception is secrets for authentication; see <citerefentry>
    <refentrytitle>ipsec.secrets</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum> </citerefentry>).
    <application>Libreswan</application> reads this file during start
    up (technically, if <application>Libreswan's</application> daemon
    <citerefentry> <refentrytitle>ipsec-pluto</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>8</manvolnum> </citerefentry> is invoked directly then
    the file <filename>ipsec.conf</filename> is not needed; however,
    this is not recommended).  Configurations can be added using eithe
    this configuration file or by using <command>ipsec whack</command>
    directly.
  </para>

  <para>
    <filename>ipsec.conf</filename> is a text file, consisting of one
    or more <emphasis>sections</emphasis>.
  </para>

  <para>
    Within the file, white space followed by <emphasis>#</emphasis>
    followed by anything to the end of the line is a comment and is
    ignored, as are empty lines that are not within a section.
  </para>

  <para>
    A line that contains <emphasis>include</emphasis> and a file name,
    separated by white space, is replaced by the contents of that
    file.  If the file name is not a full pathname, it is considered
    to be relative to the directory that contains the including file.
    Such inclusions can be nested.  Only a single filename may be
    supplied, and it may not contain white space, but it may include
    shell wildcards (see <citerefentry>
    <refentrytitle>glob</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>3</manvolnum>
    </citerefentry>); for example:
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis>include</emphasis> <filename>/etc/ipsec.d/*.conf</filename>
  </para>

  <para>
    The intention of the include facility is mostly to permit keeping
    information on connections, or sets of connections, separate from
    the main configuration file.  This permits such connection
    descriptions to be changed, copied to the other security gateways
    involved, etc., without having to constantly extract them from the
    configuration file and then insert them back into it.  Note also
    the <emphasis>also</emphasis> parameters (described below) which
    permit splitting a single logical section (e.g. a connection
    description) into several distinct sections.
  </para>

  <para>
    The first significant line of the file may specify a version of
    this specification for backwards compatibility with freeswan and
    openswan. It is ignored and unused. For compatibility with
    openswan, specify:
  </para>

  <para>
    <emphasis>version 2</emphasis>
  </para>

  <para>
    A section begins with a line of the form:
  </para>

  <para>
    <replaceable>type</replaceable> <replaceable>name</replaceable>
  </para>

  <para>
    where <replaceable>type</replaceable> indicates what type of
    section follows, and <replaceable>name</replaceable> is an
    arbitrary name that distinguishes the section from others of the
    same type.  Names must start with a letter and may contain only
    letters, digits, periods, underscores, and hyphens.  All
    subsequent non-empty lines that begin with white space are part of
    the section; comments within a section must begin with white space
    too.  There may be only one section of a given type with a given
    name.
  </para>

  <para>
    There are two types of section: a <emphasis>config</emphasis>
    section specifies general configuration information for
    <application>libreswan</application>, and a
    <emphasis>conn</emphasis> section specifies an IPsec connection.
  </para>

  <para>
    Lines within the section are generally of the form
  </para>

  <para>
    <replaceable>parameter</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable>
  </para>

  <para>
    (note the mandatory preceding white space).  There can be white
    space on either side of the <emphasis>=</emphasis>.  Parameter
    names follow the same syntax as section names, and are specific to
    a section type.  Unless otherwise explicitly specified, no
    parameter name may appear more than once in a section.
  </para>

  <para>
    An empty <replaceable>value</replaceable> stands for the empty
    string.  A non-empty <replaceable>value</replaceable> may contain
    white space only if the entire <replaceable>value</replaceable> is
    enclosed in double quotes (<emphasis>"</emphasis>); a
    <replaceable>value</replaceable> cannot itself contain a double
    quote, nor may it be continued across more than one line.
  </para>

  <para>
    Numeric values are specified to be either an integer (a sequence
    of digits) or a decimal number (sequence of digits optionally
    followed by `.' and another sequence of digits).
  </para>

  <para>
    There is currently one parameter that is available in any type of
    section:
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><envar>also</envar>=<replaceable>value</replaceable></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The <replaceable>value</replaceable> is a section name.  The
	  parameters of that section are inserted, in place, into this
	  section (i.e., as if they had been written as part of and at
	  that point in the section's definition).  The specified
	  section must exist, and must have the same section type.
	  Multiple and nested <envar>also</envar> are permitted
	  (duplicate insertions of the same section are ignored).
	  When the same <emphasis>parameter</emphasis> appears in
	  multiple sections, the first definition encountered is used.
	  This allows, for example, keeping the encryption keys for a
	  connection in a separate file from the rest of the
	  description, by using both an <envar>also</envar> parameter
	  and an <emphasis>include</emphasis> line.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Putting <envar>also</envar> at the end of the section after
	  any <emphasis>parameter</emphasis> definitions is
	  recommended.  This way, the section's
	  <emphasis>parameter</emphasis>
	  <replaceable>value</replaceable> overrides
	  <envar>also</envar> sections.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>
    Parameter names beginning with <emphasis>x-</emphasis> (or
    <emphasis>X-</emphasis>, or <emphasis>x_</emphasis>, or
    <emphasis>X_</emphasis>) are reserved for user extensions and will
    never be assigned meanings by IPsec.  Parameters with such names
    must still observe the syntax rules (limits on characters used in
    the name; no white space in a non-quoted value; no newlines or
    double quotes within the value).  All other as-yet-unused
    parameter names are reserved for future IPsec improvements.
  </para>

  <para>
    A section with name <emphasis>%default</emphasis> specifies
    defaults for sections of the same type.  For each parameter in it,
    any section of that type that does not have a parameter of the
    same name gets a copy of the one from the
    <emphasis>%default</emphasis> section.  There may be multiple
    <emphasis>%default</emphasis> sections of a given type and
    multiple default values for a given parameter (the last
    <emphasis>value</emphasis> is used).
    <emphasis>%default</emphasis> sections may not contain any
    <envar>also</envar> parameters.
  </para>

</refsect1>
