
  <title>CONN SECTIONS</title>
  <para>
    A <option>conn</option> section contains a <option>connection
    specification</option>, defining a network connection to be made
    using IPsec.  The name given is arbitrary, and is used to identify
    the connection to &ipsec.8; sub-commands.  Here's a simple
    example:
  </para>

  <programlisting><xi:include  href="exampleleftright.example"  parse="text"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting>

  <para>
    A note on terminology...  In automatic keying, there are two
    kinds of communications going on: transmission of user IP packets, and
    gateway-to-gateway negotiations for keying, rekeying, and general
    control.  The data path (a set of &ldquo;Child SAs&rdquo;) used for
    user packets is herein referred to as the &ldquo;connection&rdquo;;
    the path used for negotiations (built with &ldquo;IKE SAs&rdquo;)
    is referred to as the &ldquo;keying channel&rdquo;.
  </para>

  <para>
    To avoid trivial editing of the configuration file to suit it to each system
    involved in a connection,
    connection specifications are written in terms of
    <option>left</option>
    and
    <option>right</option>
    participants,
    rather than in terms of local and remote.
    Which participant is considered
    <option>left</option>
    or
    <option>right</option>
    is arbitrary;
    IPsec figures out which one it is being run on based on internal information.
    This permits using identical connection specifications on both ends.
    There are cases where there is no symmetry; a good convention is to
    use
    <option>left</option>
    for the local side and
    <option>right</option>
    for the remote side (the first letters are a good mnemonic).
  </para>

  <para>
    Many of the parameters relate to one participant or the other;
    only the ones for
    <option>left</option>
    are listed here, but every parameter whose name begins with
    <option>left</option>
    has a
    <option>right</option>
    counterpart,
    whose description is the same but with
    <option>left</option>
    and
    <option>right</option>
    reversed.
  </para>

  <para>
    Parameters are optional unless marked &ldquo;(required)&rdquo;
  </para>

