<varlistentry>
  <term><option>ike</option></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      IKE encryption/authentication algorithm to be used for the
      connection (phase 1 aka ISAKMP SA or IKE SA). If this option is
      not set, the builtin defaults will be used. This is the
      preferred method, and allows for gradual automatic updates using
      the same configuration. Some distributions, such as Fedora and
      RHEL/CentOS, use a System Wide Crypto Policy that sets the
      default ike= (and esp=) lines. Specifying your own ike= line
      means overriding all these system or software recommended
      defaults, but can be necessary at times. Note that libreswan
      does not support using a PRF algorithm that is different from
      the INTEGRITY (hash) algorithm by design.
    </para>
    <para> 
      The format is <option>"cipher-hash-modpgroup,
      cipher-hash-modpgroup, ..."</option> Any omitited option will
      be filled in with <option>all</option> allowed
      default values. Multiple proposals are separated by a comma. If
      an <option>ike=</option> line is specified, no
      other received proposals will be accepted than those specified
      on the IKE line.  Some examples are <option>ike=3des-sha1,aes-sha1</option>,
      <option>ike=aes</option>,
      <option>ike=aes_ctr</option>,
      <option>ike=aes_gcm256;sha2_256</option>,
      <option>ike=aes128-sha1;modp2048</option>,
      <option>ike=aes256-sha2;dh19</option>,
      <option>ike=aes128-sha1;dh22</option>,
      <option>ike=3des-md5;modp1024,aes-sha1;modp1536</option>.
      </para><para> IKEv2 allows combining elements into a single
      proposal. These can be specified by using the + symbol. An
      example is:
      <option>ike=aes_gcm+chacha20_poly1305;dh14+dh19,aes+3des-sha2+sha1;dh14</option>.
      Note that AEAD algorithms (aes_gcm, aes_ccm, chacha20_poly1305)
      and non-AEAD algorithms (aes, 3des) cannot be combined into a
      single proposal. To support aes and aes_gcm, two proposals
      separated by a comma must be used.
    </para>
    <para>
      The default IKE proposal depends on the version of libreswan
      used. It follow the recommendations of RFC4306, RFC7321 and as
      of this writing their successor draft documents RFC4306bis and
      RFC7321bis.  As for libreswan 3.32, SHA1 and MODP1536(dh5) are
      still allowed per default for backwards compatibility, but 3DES
      and MODP1024(dh2) are not allowed per default. As of libreswan
      4.x, modp1024(dh2) support is no longer compiled in at all. For
      IKEv2, the defaults include AES, AES-GCM, DH14 and stronger, and
      SHA2.  The default key size is 256 bits. The default AES_GCM ICV
      is 16 bytes.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that AES-GCM is an AEAD algorithm, meaning that it performs
      encryption+authentication in one step. This means that AES-GCM
      must not specify an authentication algorithm. However, for IKE
      it does require a PRF function, so the second argument to an
      AEAD algorithm denotes the PRF. So ike=aes_gcm-sha2_256 means
      propose AES_GCM with SHA2_256 as the prf. Note that for
      esp, there is no prf, so AES-GCM is specified for ESP as
      esp=aes_gcm. The AES-GCM and AES-CCM algorithms support 8,12 and
      16 byte ICV's.  These can be specified using a postfix, for
      example aes_gcm_a (for 8), aes_gcm_b (for 12) and aes_gcm_c (for
      16).  The default (aes_gcm without postfix) refers to the 16
      byte ICV version. RFC 8247 only mandates the 16 byte ICV version
      is implemented, so it is recommended to NOT use the 8 or 12 byte
      versions of GCM or CCM. These versions are NOT included in the
      default proposal list and will be removed in a future version.
    </para>
    <para>
      Weak algorithms are regularly removed from libreswan. Currently,
      1DES and modp768(DH1) have been removed and modp1024(DH2) has
      been disabled at compile time. Additionally, MD5 and SHA1 will
      be removed within the next few years. Null encryption is
      available, and should only be used for testing or benchmarking
      purposes. Please do not request for insecure algorithms to be
      re-added to libreswan. IKEv1 has been disabled per default, and
      will soon no longer be compiled in by default.
    </para>
    <para>
      For all Diffie-Hellman groups, the "dh" keyword can be used
      instead of the "modp" keyword. For example
      <option>ike=3des-sha1-dh19</option>. Diffie-Hellman groups
      19,20 and 21 from RFC-5903 are supported. Curve25519 from
      RFC-8031 is supported as "dh31". Curve448 and GOST DH groups are
      not yet supported in libreswan because these are not supported
      yet in the NSS crypto library.
    </para>
    <para>
      Diffie-Hellman groups 22, 23 and 24 from RFC-5114 are
      implemented but not compiled in by default.  These DH groups are
      extremely controversial and MUST NOT be used unless forced
      (administratively) by the other party. This is further
      documented in RFC 8247, but the summary is that it cannot be
      proven that these DH groups do not contain a cryptographic
      trapdoor (a backdoor by the USG who provided these primes
      without revealing the seeds and generation process used).
    </para>
    <para>
      The modp syntax will be removed in favour of the dh syntax in
      the future
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

