<varlistentry>
  <term>
    <option>ipsec-interface</option>
  </term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Create or use an existing virtual interface <option>ipsecXXX</option>
      for "Routing based VPNs" (as opposed to "Policy based VPNs").
      Valid options are <option>yes</option>, <option>no</option> or a
      number. When using a number, the IPsec interface created and/or
      used will use that number as part of the interface name. For
      example setting <option>ipsec-interface=5</option>
      will create and/or use the <option>ipsec5</option>
      interface. The value <option>0</option> cannot be
      used and is interpreted as <option>no</option>. The value
      <option>yes</option> is interpreted as the number 1, and
      thus will use the interface named
      <option>ipsec1</option>. An IP address can be configured for
      this interface via the <option>interface-ip=</option> option.
    </para>
    <para>
      The ipsec-interface is used to route outbound traffic that needs
      to be encrypted, and will decrypt inbound traffic that arrives
      on this interface. All traffic that is routed to this interface
      will be automatically encrypted providing the IPsec SA policy
      covers this traffic. Traffic not matching the IPsec SA will be
      dropped. Tools such as tcpdump, iptables, ifconfig and tools
      that need traffic counters can be used on all cleartext
      pre-encrypt and post-decrypt traffic on the device. When
      <option>leftsubnet=</option> is equal to
      <option>rightsubnet=</option>, the routing needs to be
      managed by an external routing daemon or manually by the
      administrator.
    </para>
    <para>
      This option is currently only supported on Linux kernels 4.19 or
      later when compiled with XFRMi support
      (<option>CONFIG_XFRM_INTERFACE</option>). The number of the
      ipsecX device corresponds with the <option>XFRM
      IF_ID</option> policy option of the IPsec SA in the Linux
      kernel. On Linux, XFRMi interfaces can be managed by libreswan
      automatically or can be preconfigured on the system using the
      existing init system or via networking tools such as
      systemd-networkd and NetworkManager. The _updown script handles
      certain Linux specific interfaces settings required for proper
      functioning, such as forwarding and routing rules for IPsec
      traffic.
    </para>
    <para>
      The ipsec-interface=0 will create an interface with the same
      name as the old KLIPS interface, ipsec0.  This interface name
      should only be used when required for migration from KLIPS to
      XFRM interfaces.  Since XFRM IF_ID and marking cannot use 0,
      this is mapped to 16384. This means that the devices ipsec0 and
      ipsec16384 cannot both be in use.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>
