<varlistentry>
  <term>
    <emphasis>leftprotoport</emphasis>
  </term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      allowed protocols and ports over connection, also called Port
      Selectors. The argument is in the form <emphasis>protocol</emphasis>,
      which can be a number or a name
      that will be looked up in <emphasis>/etc/protocols</emphasis>,
      such as <emphasis>leftprotoport=icmp</emphasis>, or in the form of
      <emphasis>protocol/port</emphasis>, such as <emphasis>tcp/smtp</emphasis>.
      Ports can be defined as a number
      (eg. 25) or as a name (eg smtp) which will be looked up in
      <emphasis>/etc/services</emphasis>. A special keyword
      <emphasis>%any</emphasis> can be used to allow all
      ports of a certain protocol. The most common use of this option
      is for L2TP connections to only allow l2tp packets (UDP port
      1701), eg: <emphasis>leftprotoport=17/1701</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      To filter on specific icmp type and code, use the higher 8 bits
      for type and the lower 8 bits for port. For example, to allow
      icmp echo packets (type 8, code 0) the 'port' would be 0x0800,
      or 2048 in decimal, so you configure
      <emphasis>leftprotoport=icmp/2048</emphasis>. Similarly, to
      allow ipv6-icmp Neighbour Discovery which has type 136 (0x88)
      and code 0(0x00) this becomes 0x8800 or in decimal 34816
      resulting in <emphasis>leftprotoport=ipv6-icmp/34816</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Some clients, notably older Windows XP and some Mac OSX clients,
      use a random high port as source port. In those cases
      <emphasis>rightprotoport=17/%any</emphasis> can be used to allow
      all UDP traffic on the connection.  Note that this option is
      part of the proposal, so it cannot be arbitrarily left out if
      one end does not care about the traffic selection over this
      connection - both peers have to agree. The Port Selectors show
      up in the output of <command>ipsec status</command>
      eg:<emphasis>"l2tp":
      193.110.157.131[@aivd.libreswan.org]:7/1701...%any:17/1701</emphasis>
      This option only filters outbound traffic.  Inbound traffic
      selection must still be based on firewall rules activated by an
      updown script. The variables $PLUTO_MY_PROTOCOL,
      $PLUTO_PEER_PROTOCOL, $PLUTO_MY_PORT, and $PLUTO_PEER_PORT are
      available for use in <emphasis>updown</emphasis> scripts. Older
      workarounds for bugs involved a setting of
      <emphasis>17/0</emphasis> to denote <emphasis>any single UDP
      port</emphasis> (not UDP port 0). Some clients, most notably
      OSX, uses a random high port, instead of port 1701 for L2TP.
    </para>

    <important>
      <title>
	<code>use with leftsubnet</code>
      </title>
      <para>
	With IKEv2, the <code>leftsubnet</code> specification can
	include the protocol and port.  Combining that syntax with
	<code>protoport</code> is not supported.
      </para>
    </important>

  </listitem>
</varlistentry>
