<varlistentry>
  <term>
    <option>left</option>
  </term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      (required) the IP address or DNS hostname of the left
      participant's public-network interface, Currently, IPv4 and IPv6
      IP addresses are supported. If a DNS hostname is used, it will
      be resolved to an IP address on load time, and whenever a
      connection is rekeying or restarting (such as when restarted via
      a DPD failure detection). This allows one to use a DNS hostname
      when the endpoint is on a dynamic IP address.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are several magic values.  If it is
      <option>%defaultroute</option>, <option>left</option> will be
      filled in automatically with the local address of the
      default-route interface (as determined at IPsec startup time);
      this also overrides any value supplied for
      <option>leftnexthop</option>.  (Either <option>left</option> or
      <option>right</option> may be <option>%defaultroute</option>,
      but not both.)  The value <option>%any</option> signifies an
      address to be filled in (by automatic keying) during
      negotiation.  The value <option>%opportunistic</option>
      signifies that both <option>left</option> and
      <option>leftnexthop</option> are to be filled in (by automatic
      keying) from DNS data for <option>left</option>'s client.  The
      value can also contain the interface name, which will then later
      be used to obtain the IP address from to fill in. For example
      <option>%ppp0</option>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The values <option>%group</option> and
      <option>%opportunisticgroup</option> makes this a policy group
      conn: one that will be instantiated into a regular or
      opportunistic conn for each CIDR block listed in the policy
      group file with the same name as the conn.
    </para>
    <para>
      If using IP addresses in combination with NAT, always use the
      actual local machine's (NATed) IP address, and if the remote (eg
      right=) is NATed as well, the remote's public
      (<option>not</option> NATed) IP address. Note that this makes
      the configuration no longer symmetrical on both sides, so you
      cannot use an identical configuration file on both hosts.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>
