<varlistentry>
  <term>
    <emphasis>nic-offload</emphasis>
  </term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Set the method of Network Interface Controller (NIC) hardware
      offload for ESP/AH packet processing.  Acceptable values are
      <emphasis>no</emphasis> (the default),
      <emphasis>crypto</emphasis> or <emphasis>packet</emphasis>.  The
      value <emphasis>yes</emphasis> is a backwards compatible value
      for <emphasis>crypto</emphasis>.  The nic-offload option is
      separate from any CPU hardware offload available.  When set to
      <emphasis>crypto</emphasis>, only cryptographic operations are
      offloaded to the NIC card.  When set to
      <emphasis>packet</emphasis>, the entire packet processing
      including the encryption/decryption is offloaded to the NIC
      card.
    </para>
    <para>
      Crypto nic-offload is available starting Linux 4.13 using the
      XFRM IPsec stack.  Packet nic-offload is available starting
      Linux 6.3.  Both require that the Linux kernel is compiled with
      the options CONFIG_XFRM_OFFLOAD, CONFIG_INET_ESP_OFFLOAD and
      CONFIG_INET6_ESP_OFFLOAD.  Network card support can be seen by
      the precense of the <emphasis>esp-hw-offload</emphasis>
      capability using the <emphasis>ethtool -S</emphasis> command.
      The Linux kernel attempts to fall back from crypto hardware
      offload to software, but only for some algorithms (AEADs only?).
      There is no fallback from packet offload to crypto offload.  At
      the time of libreswan 5.0, we are only aware of the
      Nvidia/Mellanox ConnectX-7 (and to some extend ConnectX-6) cards
      supporting packet offload.
    </para>
    <para>
      In general, it makes no sense to try to offload older (non-AEAD)
      cryptographic algorithms such as AES-CBC or 3DES, as these
      algorithms are so much slower than AEAD algorithms (such as
      AES-GCM) that one would gain more performance by switching the
      algorithm to AEAD than by offloading.  As such, AES-CBC tends to
      not be implemented in offload hardware.  This option has also no
      effect on IKE packets, which are never offloaded, although IKE
      encryption does use supported CPU hardware instructions, such as
      AESNI.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>
