  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>seccomp</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Set the seccomp kernel syscall whitelisting feature. When set to
<option>enabled</option>, if pluto calls a syscall that is
not on the compiled-in whitelist, the kernel will assume an exploit is
attempting to use pluto for malicious access to the system and terminate
the pluto daemon. When set to <option>tolerant</option>,
the kernel will only block the rogue syscall and pluto will attempt to
continue. If set to <option>disabled</option>, pluto is
allowed to call any syscall offered by the kernel, although it might be
restricted via other security mechanisms, such as capabilities, SElinux,
AppArmor or other OS security features.</para>

<para>By default, seccomp is disabled, as there is a significant performance
penalty, custom updown scripts could trigger false positives, and
system library updates could also trigger false positives. A false positive
(or real malicious remote code execution of a bad syscall) will cause the
pluto daemon to crash or hang.</para>

<para><option>Warning:</option> The restrictions of pluto
are inherited by the updown scripts, so these scripts are also not
allowed to use syscalls that are forbidden for pluto.</para>

<para>
To see if a seccomp rule got triggered, you must run with seccomp=enabled,
and keep an eye on <option>type=SECCOMP</option> messages in the
audit log (usually <option>/var/log/audit/audit.log</option>. Note
that logging can be delayed by many seconds.</para>

<para>
  This feature can be tested using <command>ipsec whack
  --seccomp-crashtest</command>. <option>Warning: </option> With
  seccomp=enabled, pluto will be terminated by the kernel. With
  seccomp=tolerant or seccomp=disabled, pluto will report the results
  of the seccomp test. SECCOMP will log the forbidden syscall numbers
  to the audit log, but only with seccomp=enabled. The tool
  scmp_sys_resolver from the libseccomp development package can be
  used to translate the syscall number into a name. See
  programs/pluto/pluto_seccomp.c for the list of allowed syscalls.
  </para>


  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
