<refsect1 id='choosing_a_connection'>
  <title>
    CHOOSING A CONNECTION [THIS SECTION IS EXTREMELY OUT OF DATE
  </title>
  <para>
    When choosing a connection to apply to an outbound packet caught
    with a <emphasis>%trap,</emphasis> the system prefers
    the one with the most specific eroute that includes the packet's
    source and destination IP addresses.  Source subnets are examined
    before destination subnets.  For initiating, only routed
    connections are considered. For responding, unrouted but added
    connections are considered.
  </para>
  <para>
    When choosing a connection to use to respond to a negotiation
    that doesn't match an ordinary conn, an opportunistic connection may
    be instantiated. Eventually, its instance will be /32 -&gt; /32, but
    for earlier stages of the negotiation, there will not be enough
    information about the client subnets to complete the
    instantiation.
  </para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='files'>
  <title>
    FILES
  </title>
  <para>
    <filename>/etc/ipsec.conf</filename>
    <filename>/etc/ipsec.d/policies/clear</filename>
    <filename>/etc/ipsec.d/policies/clear-or-private</filename>
    <filename>/etc/ipsec.d/policies/private-or-clear</filename>
    <filename>/etc/ipsec.d/policies/private</filename>
    <filename>/etc/ipsec.d/policies/block</filename>
  </para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='see_also'>
  <title>
    SEE ALSO
  </title>
  <para>
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_rsasigkey</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
  </para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='history'>
  <title>
    HISTORY
  </title>
  <para>
    Designed for the FreeS/WAN project &lt;<ulink
    url='https://www.freeswan.org'>https://www.freeswan.org</ulink>&gt;
    by Henry Spencer.
  </para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='bugs'>
  <title>
    BUGS
  </title>
  <para>
    Before reporting new bugs, please ensure you are using the latest
    version of Libreswan.
  </para>

  <para>
    When <emphasis>type</emphasis> or
    <emphasis>failureshunt</emphasis> is set to
    <emphasis>drop</emphasis> or <emphasis>reject,</emphasis>
    Libreswan blocks outbound packets using eroutes, but assumes
    inbound blocking is handled by the firewall. Libreswan offers
    firewall hooks via an &ldquo;updown&rdquo; script.  However, the
    default <command>ipsec _updown</command> provides no help in
    controlling a modern firewall.
  </para>

  <para>
    Including attributes of the keying channel (authentication
    methods, <emphasis>ikelifetime</emphasis>, etc.) as an
    attribute of a connection, rather than of a participant pair, is
    dubious and incurs limitations.
  </para>

  <para>
    The use of <emphasis>%any</emphasis> with the <emphasis>protoport=</emphasis>
    option is ambiguous. Should the SA permits any port through or should
    the SA negotiate any single port through?  The first is a basic conn with
    a wildcard. The second is a template. The second is the current behaviour,
    and it's wrong for quite a number of uses involving TCP. The keyword
    <emphasis>%one</emphasis> may be introduced in the
    future to separate these two cases.
  </para>

  <para>
    It would be good to have a line-continuation syntax, especially
    for the very long lines involved in RSA signature keys.
  </para>

  <para>
    The ability to specify different identities, <emphasis>authby</emphasis>,
    and public keys for different automatic-keyed connections between
    the same participants is misleading; this doesn't work dependably
    because the identity of the participants is not known early enough.
    This is especially awkward for the &ldquo;Road Warrior&rdquo; case,
    where the remote IP address is specified as <literal>0.0.0.0</literal>,
    and that is considered to be the &ldquo;participant&rdquo; for such
    connections.
  </para>

  <para>
    If conns are to be added before DNS is available, <emphasis>left=</emphasis>
    <emphasis>FQDN</emphasis>, <emphasis>leftnextop=</emphasis><emphasis>FQDN</emphasis>,
    and <emphasis>leftrsasigkey=%dnsonload</emphasis> will fail.
    <citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_pluto</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    does not actually use the public key for our side of a conn but it
    isn't generally known at a add-time which side is ours (Road
    Warrior and Opportunistic conns are currently exceptions).
  </para>

</refsect1>
