<varlistentry>
  <term>
    <option>virtual-private</option>
  </term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      contains the networks that are allowed as (left|right)subnet=
      for the remote clients when using the <option>vhost:</option> or
      <option>vnet:</option> keywords in the
      <option>(left|right)subnet=</option> parameters.  In other
      words, the address ranges that may live behind a NAT router
      through which a client connects.  This value is usually set to
      all the RFC-1918 address space, excluding the space used in the
      local subnet behind the NAT (An IP address cannot live at two
      places at once).  IPv4 address ranges are denoted as
      <option>%v4:a.b.c.d/mm</option> and IPv6 is denoted as
      <option>%v6:aaaa::bbbb:cccc:dddd:eeee/mm</option>. One can
      exclude subnets by using the <option>!</option>.  For example,
      if the VPN server is giving access to 192.168.1.0/24, this
      option should be set to:
      <option>virtual-private=%v4:10.0.0.0/8,%v4:192.168.0.0/16,%v4:172.16.0.0/12,%v4:!192.168.1.0/24</option>.
      This parameter is only needed on the server side and not on the
      client side that resides behind the NAT router, as the client
      will just use its IP address for the inner IP setting.  This
      parameter may eventually become per-connection. See also
      <option>leftsubnet=</option>
    </para>
    <para>
      Note: It seems that T-Mobile in the US and Rogers/Fido in Canada
      have started using 25.0.0.0/8 as their pre-NAT range. This range
      technically belongs to the Defence Interoperable Network
      Services Authority (DINSA), an agency of the Ministry of Defence
      of the United Kingdom. The network range seems to not have been
      announced for decades, which is probably why these organisations
      "borrowed" this range. To support roadwarriors on these 3G
      networks, you might have to add it to the virtual-private= line.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>
