  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>vti-interface</option></term>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      This option is deprecated. See <option>ipsec-interface</option>
      instead.
    </para>
    <para>
      This option is used to create "Routing based VPNs"
      (as opposed to "Policy based VPNs"). It will create a new interface
      that can be used to route traffic in for encryption/decryption. The Virtual
      Tunnel Interface ("VTI") interface name is used to for all IPsec SA's created by
      this connection. This requires that the connection also enables either
      the <option>mark=</option> or <option>mark-in= /
      mark-out-</option> option(s). All traffic marked with the proper MARKs
      will be automatically encrypted if there is an IPsec SA policy covering the
      source/destination traffic. Tools such as tcpdump and iptables can be
      used on all cleartext pre-encrypt and post-decrypt traffic on the device.
      See the libreswan wiki for example configurations that use VTI.
    </para>
    <para>
      VTI interfaces are currently only supported on Linux with XFRM. The
      _updown script handles certain Linux specific interfaces settings
      required for proper functioning (disable_policy, rp_filter,
      forwarding, etc). Interface names are limited to 16 characters and
      may not allow all characters to be used. If marking and
      <option>vti-routing=yes</option> is used, no manual iptables should
      be required. However, administrators can use the iptables mangle table
      to mark traffic manually if desired.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
    <term><option>vti-routing</option></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Whether or not to add network rules or routes for IPsec
	SA's to the respective VTI devices. Valid values are
	<option>yes</option> (the default) or <option>no</option>.
	When using "routing based VPNs" with a subnets policy of 0.0.0.0/0,
	this setting needs to set to <option>no</option> to prevent
	imploding the tunnel, and the administrator is expected to manually
	add ip rules and ip routes to configure what traffic must be encrypted.
	When set to <option>yes</option>, the _updown script will
	automatically route the leftsubnet/rightsubnet traffic into the
	VTI device specified with <option>vti-interface</option>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><option>vti-shared</option></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Whether or not the VTI device is shared amongst connections.
	Valid values are <option>no</option> (the default) or
	<option>yes</option>. When set to no, the VTI device is automatically
	deleted if the connection is a single non-instantiated connection. If a
	connection instantiates (eg right=%any) then this option has no effect, as
	the VTI device is not removed as it is shared with multiple roadwarriors.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
