  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>ike</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>IKE encryption/authentication algorithm to be used
for the connection (phase 1 aka ISAKMP SA).  The format is
<emphasis remap='I'>"cipher-hash;modpgroup, cipher-hash;modpgroup, ..."</emphasis>
Any left out option will be filled in with all allowed default
options. Multiple proposals are separated by a comma. If an
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=</emphasis>
line is specified, no other received proposals will be accepted.
Formerly there was a distinction (by using a <emphasis remap='B'>"!"</emphasis> symbol) between
"strict mode" or not. That mode has been obsoleted. If an <emphasis remap='B'>ike=</emphasis> option is
specified, the mode is always strict, meaning no other received proposals will be accepted.
Some examples are
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=3des-sha1,aes-sha1</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes_ctr</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes_gcm256-sha2</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes128-md5;modp2048</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes256-sha2;dh19</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes128-sha1;dh22</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=3des-md5;modp1024,aes-sha1;modp1536</emphasis>.
The options must be suitable as a value of
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_spi</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>'s
<option>--ike</option> option. The default IKE proposal depends on the version of libreswan
used. It follow the recommendations of RFC4306, RFC7321 and as of this writing their successor
draft documents RFC4306bis and RFC7321bis. For IKEv1, SHA1 and MODP1536 are still allowed per
default for backwards compatibility, but 3DES and MODP1024 are not allowed per default. IKEv2's
minimum is AES, MODP2048 and SHA2. The default key size is 256 bits. The default AES_GCM ICV
is 16 bytes.</para>

<para>Note that AES-GCM is an AEAD algorithm, meaning that it performs encryption+authentication in one step. This
means that AES-GCM must not specify an authentication algorithm. However, it does require a PRF function, so
the second argument to an AEAD algorithm denotes the PRF. So ike=aes_gcm-sha2 means propose AES_GCM with no
authentication and using SHA2 as the prf. Note that for phase2alg, there is no prf, so AES-GCM is
specified for ESP as phase2alg=aes_gcm-null. The AES-GCM and AES-CCM algorithms support 8,12 and 16 byte ICV's.
These can be specified using a postfix, for example aes_gcm_a (for 8), aes_gcm_b (for 12) and aes_gcm_c (for 16).
The default (aes_gcm without postfix) refers to the 16 byte ICV version. It is strongly recommended to NOT use
the 8 or 12 byte versions of GCM or CCM.
</para>
<para>
Weak algorithms are regularly removed from libreswan. Currently, 1DES and modp768 have been removed and modp1024
will be removed in the near future. Additionally, md5 and sha1 will be removed within the next few years. Null
encryption is available, and should only be used for testing or benchmarking purposes. Please do not request for
insecure algorithms to be re-added to libreswan.
</para>
<para>Diffie-Hellman groups 19,20 and 21 from RFC- 5903 and 22, 23 and 24 from RFC-5114 are also supported.
For all groups, the "dh" keyword can be used. For the MODP based groups, the modp= keyword can be used. for
example <emphasis>ike=3des-sha1;dh19</emphasis>.
The RFC-5114 DH groups are extremely controversial and MUST NOT be used unless forced (administratively) by
the other party. Support for these groups will most likely be removed in 2017, as it cannot be proven these
DH groups do not have a cryptographic trapdoor embedded in them (a backdoor by the USG who provided these
primes without revealing the seeds and generation process used). Due the the weakness od DH22, support for
this group is not compiled in by default and can be re-enabled using USE_DH22=true.
</para>
<para>The modp syntax will be removed in favour of the dh syntax in the future</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

