  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap='B'>ike</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>IKE encryption/authentication algorithm to be used
for the connection (phase 1 aka ISAKMP SA).  The format is
<emphasis remap='I'>"cipher-hash;modpgroup, cipher-hash;modpgroup, ..."</emphasis>
Any left out option will be filled in with all allowed default
options. Multiple proposals are separated by a comma. If an
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=</emphasis>
line is specified, no other received proposals will be accepted.
Formerly there was a distinction (by using a <emphasis remap='B'>"!"</emphasis> symbol) between
"strict mode" or not. That mode has been obsoleted. If an <emphasis remap='B'>ike=</emphasis> option is
specified, the mode is always strict, meaning no other received proposals will be accepted.
Some examples are
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=3des-sha1,aes-sha1</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes_ctr</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes_gcm256-sha2</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes128-md5;modp2048</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=aes128-sha1;dh22</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap='B'>ike=3des-md5;modp1024,aes-sha1;modp1536</emphasis>.
The options must be suitable as a value of
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>ipsec_spi</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>'s
<option>--ike</option> option. The default is to use IKE, and to allow all combinations of:
<literallayout remap='.nf'><emphasis remap='B'>
                cipher:                 3des or aes128 or aes256
                hash:                   sha1 or md5
                pfsgroup (DHgroup):     modp1024 or modp1536 or modp2048
</emphasis></literallayout>

Note that AES-GCM is an AEAD algorithm, meaning that it performs encryption+authentication in one step. This
means that AES-GCM must not specify an authentication algorithm. However, it does require a PRF function, so
the second argument to an AEAD algorithm denotes the PRF. So ike=aes_gcm-sha2 means propose AES_GCM with no
authentication and using SHA2 as the prf. Note that for phase2alg, there is no prf, so AES-GCM is
specified for ESP as phase2alg=aes_gcm-null. The AES-GCM and AES-CCM algorithms support 8,12 and 16 byte ICV's.
These can be specified using a postfix, for example aes_gcm_a (for 8), aes_gcm_b (for 12) and aes_gcm_c (for 16).
The default (aes_gcm without postfix) refers to the 16 byte ICV version. It is strongly recommended to NOT use
the 8 or 12 byte versions of GCM or CCM.
</para>
<para>
Weak algorithms are regularly removed from libreswan. Currently, 1DES and modp768 have been removed and modp1024
will be removed in the near future. Additionally, md5 and sha1 will be removed within the next few years. Null
encryption is available, and should only be used for testing or benchmarking purposes. Please do not request for
insecure algorithms to be re-added to libreswan.
</para>
<para>Diffie-Hellman groups 22, 23 and 24 are also implemented as per RFC-5114. Instead of the modp
key syntax, use the "dh" keyword, for example <emphasis>ike=3des-sha1;dh23</emphasis>
</para>
<para>The modp syntax will be removed in favour of the dh syntax.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

